<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[heterodoxic]]></title>
  <link href="http://mrelectron.github.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mrelectron.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-04-25T15:33:10+10:00</updated>
  <id>http://mrelectron.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[MAB]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to write a Film Review]]></title>
    <link href="http://mrelectron.github.com/blog/2012/01/29/how-to-write-a-film-review/"/>
    <updated>2012-01-29T23:21:00+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://mrelectron.github.com/blog/2012/01/29/how-to-write-a-film-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The information below is from the following two websites <a href="http://www.spiritofbaraka.com/how-to-write-a-movie-review.aspx">spiritofbaraka.com</a> &amp; <a href="http://www.moviefilmreview.com/ht">moviefilmreview.com</a>.</p>

<p>Writing a movie review is a great way of expressing your opinion of a movie.  The purpose of most movie reviews is to help the reader in determining whether they want to watch, rent or buy the movie.  The review should give enough details about the movie that the reader can make an informed decision, without giving anyway any essentials such as the plot or any surprises.  Below are our guidelines and tips for writing a good movie review.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Before you write a Word</h2>

<ul>
<li><p>Watch the movie: The first step in writing the review is to watch the movie.  Watch the movie in a relaxed environment you are familiar with.  You do not want to be distracted by an unfamiliar room.  Watching the movie a second time will help you absorb a lot more detail about the movie.  Most movie reviewers take notes as they watch the movie review. Think about what you like and don&#8217;t like about it. Try to remember these things, because you will need them during the writing part.</p></li>
<li><p>Go home, and write down all the information that you gathered during the movie. Let all the information sit for up to a day because you need time to think over the movie. But, don&#8217;t let yourself take more than a day, because if you wait too long, you tend to lose interest and forget important things that you felt.</p></li>
<li><p>Write all the information down in a format that is readable for others. Remember to include a basic summary for people who haven&#8217;t heard of the movie, but remember to not give away the ending, or any other part that they wouldn&#8217;t want to have ruined for them.</p></li>
<li><p>Remember to aim for about 600-700 words for the entire review.</p></li>
<li><p>Hand out copies of your review to other people, so they can have the chance to read your opinion, and after time, you may start to get people wanting more and more reviews.</p></li>
<li><p>Remember to try reviewing every movie you see, because when you get into the habit, it will become easier.</p></li>
<li><p>Once you gain more confidence in your reviews, try to match the tone of each with the style of the movie. For example, a humorous writing style would work well for a comedy, whereas a more serious tone would be good for writing a drama review.</p></li>
</ul>


<h2>Writing the Review</h2>

<ol>
<li><p>Give your opinion: Most movie reviewers will give their opinion of the movie.  This is important as the reviewer can express the elements of the movie they enjoyed or disliked.  However, as in all good journalism, the reviewer should also give impartial details, and allow the reader to make their own mind over an issue the reader liked or disliked.  Opinions should be explained to allow the reader to determine whether they would agree with your opinion .
Many regular movie reviewers will develop a following.  If one can find a reviewer who shares a similar taste in films, one can confidently follow the reviewers recommendations.</p></li>
<li><p>Who is your audience?: You need to consider who your likely readers are.  Writing a movie review for children requires a different approach than if writing for a movie club.  Ensure you report on the factors that matter to your likely audience.</p></li>
<li><p>Give an outline: Give the outline of the movie, but don&#8217;t give away essential details such as the end or any surprises.  If there is a big surprise you want to entice readers by telling them something special happens, just don&#8217;t say what.</p></li>
<li><p>Actors: If the movie contains actors, as most do, detail who is starring in the movie and how well you think they acted.</p></li>
<li><p>Structure: Did the movie follow a regular predictable story line, or did it get you thinking like a Quentin Tarantino movie?</p></li>
</ol>


<p>6.Cinematography and lighting: Give details about how well the movie was shot and directed.  Was the lighting good in the moody scenes?</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Music: Did the movie have its own score like Koyaanisqatsi or ET, or did it feature songs from popular artists?</p></li>
<li><p>Read, read and read: Read and check your review thoroughly.  It can be embarrassing to find errors in your work after it has been published.  This is especially important for reviews that will be published on the Internet, as search engines are always looking for the correct spellings of key words.</p></li>
</ol>


<h2>Format</h2>

<ul>
<li><p>Title of the movie</p></li>
<li><p>Paragraph 1:You will need to include the following: name of the film, prominent stars of the film, basic setting ( time and place), and type of film ( comedy, adventure, drama, etc.)</p></li>
<li><p>Paragraph 2:You will need to write a plot summary for the movie. Do not reveal the ending. Discuss at least 5 events and be sure to cover the entire scope of the movie, except the very end.</p></li>
<li><p>Paragraph 3: Discuss one aspect of filmmaking. You may choose from acting, direction, editing, costume design, set design, photography, background music, or anything else you may think of. Be sure that you are specific and cite examples from the movie.</p></li>
<li><p>Paragraph 4: Discuss another aspect of filmmaking. You may choose from acting, direction, editing, costume design, set design, photography, background music, or anything else you may think of, but obviously choose something different from what you discussed in the previous paragraph. Be sure that you are specific and cite examples from the movie.</p></li>
<li><p>Paragraph 5: Give your overall reaction to the film as well as your opinion on the quality of the film. also include your recommendations for potential viewers.</p></li>
</ul>


<h2>Example:Forrest Gump</h2>

<p>&#8220;Life is like a box of chocolates. You never know what you&#8217;re gonna get.&#8221; However, when you watch Forrest Gump starring Tom Hanks as Forrest and Robin Wright as Jenny, you know you are going to get a lot of laughs and even a few tears.</p>

<p>The screenplay for the 1994 movie was written by Eric Roth, based on the novel by Winston Groom. The story follows Forrest through 30 years of trials and tribulations, placing Forrest within historical moments of history, and in pursuit of his one dream-his &#8220;most special friend,&#8221; Jenny. According to the Washington Post, Forrest Gump won Oscar awards for Best Picture, Best Actor (Hanks), Best Director (Robert Zemeckis), Film Editing, Visual Effects and Adapted Screenplay. The movie was well deserving of these awards since the acting and the visual effects were extraordinary.</p>

<p>The films&#8217; actors success in portraying their characters is a major factor in the film&#8217;s awards. Tom Hanks and Robin Wright worked well together, just like &#8220;peas and carrots.&#8221; The on-screen chemistry between the two was phenomenal. I felt a real connection between the two, finding myself mad at Jenny when she blew Forrest off and in tears when he told her that he was heading to Vietnam. Mokui&#8217;s Movie Review states &#8220;Tom Hanks IS Forrest Gump&#8230;He breathes life into the guy and you will feel what Forrest feels&#8221; (1994, par 1).</p>

<p>James Berardinelli states, &#8220;Robin Wright gives the best performance of her career, surpassing what she accomplished in The Playboys&#8221; (1994, par2). Another performance that stands out is that of Gary Sinise. Sinise plays the part of Lieutenant Dan Taylor, whose life is saved by Forrest during the Vietnam War. James Berardinelli writes, &#8220;In this movie, his Lieutenant Dan Taylor is riveting&#8221; (1994, par 3). I thought that Sinise was quite convincing with his emotions throughout the movie, as if he was really a disabled vet who had lost both legs in the war.</p>

<p>Just as good as the actors were those working behind the scenes with the special effects. Throughout Forrest Gump the special effects were incredible. During Lieutenant Taylor&#8217;s scenes, I was convinced that he really didn&#8217;t have legs. I was studying the scenes, looking for any signs of legs, trying to figure out how it was done.</p>

<p>It turns out that each and every frame was painted over to give it the true to life values that it holds. Also bringing the movie more credibility was the ability to place Forrest in history making events. These events ranged from Forrest teaching Elvis how to swing his hips to meeting Presidents for various accomplishments. These television clips of Forrest were done with such finesse that they look real. Critic Brian Webster (2003) states, &#8220;This is handled virtually flawlessly; if you didn&#8217;t know better, you&#8217;d believe that a fellow named Gump really did tell President Lyndon Johnson that he had been shot in the rump while acting heroically in Vietnam&#8221; (par 2). Rolling Stone (2003) states, &#8220;The effects dazzle, though never at the expense of the story&#8221; (Travers, par 2).</p>

<p>This story, complete with the Oscar winning performances in both acting and special effects is perfect for those in need of a dose of goodness. My family enjoys watching Forrest Gump together for rejuvenation, to view someone with true values of honesty, friendship and family. Forrest, with his heart of gold and his low IQ, never gives up. He always looks for the best in every scenario. The movie opens with a feather floating down over the city, landing at Forrest&#8217;s feet. Near the end of the story, Forrest questions, &#8220;Do we each have a destiny - or do we just float around accidental, like on a breeze?&#8221; As you are contemplating this question, the feather reappears and floats through the countryside right up into the ending credits.</p>

<p>Below is a censored version of my previous <a href="http://www.moviefilmreview.com/ht">post</a> on George Carlin. It has been censored, in protest of a bill that gives any corporation and the US government the power to censor the internet&#8211;a bill that could pass THIS WEEK. To see the uncensored text, and to stop internet censorship, visit:
<a href="http://www.spiritofbaraka.com/how-to-write-a-movie-review.aspx">americancensorship.org</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[SOPA - Redaction &amp; Censorship]]></title>
    <link href="http://mrelectron.github.com/blog/2011/12/14/sopa-redaction-and-censorship/"/>
    <updated>2011-12-14T16:02:00+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://mrelectron.github.com/blog/2011/12/14/sopa-redaction-and-censorship</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Below is a censored version of my previous <a href="http://heterodoxic.com/blog/2011/12/07/carlin-religious-bullshit/">post</a> on George Carlin. It has been censored, in protest of a bill that gives any corporation and the US government the power to censor the internet&#8211;a bill that could pass THIS WEEK. To see the uncensored text, and to stop internet censorship, visit:
<a href="http://americancensorship.org/posts/9642/uncensor">americancensorship.org</a>.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>I █████ ████ 10 ██████ █████ by the ████ ██████ ██████ on ██████ Bay. Its █████ and █████ ███████ for the ███████████ and █████████ █████. The █████ and █████ are ████ but the █████ is █████ ████████.</p>

<p>I don’t ████ ████ the ████ of his █████ is ████. For ████ its █████ he is 2nd on ████ ████ of the 100 ████████ ███████ █████████.</p>

<p>█████ ███████ ████ up, I █████ 100’s of ██████ of ██████ on ███████.</p>

<p>████ ████ ████ the new █████ █████ tag, █████ is ██████ ████, so now you can put a █████ on ████ ███████ ████ the ████ ████ as you ████ to be ████ to do ████ an █████. I █████ █████ are ████ ██████ ████ █████ ███████ ███████ - I █████████ use ██████ (I █████ ████ ██████ use ███████ - but the ██████ ████ ██████ of at ███████ and ███████ is now ████ a ████ ███████ ██████ and ████████ hog - a ██████ █████.) and it █████ ████.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Carlin - Religious Bullshit]]></title>
    <link href="http://mrelectron.github.com/blog/2011/12/07/carlin-religious-bullshit/"/>
    <updated>2011-12-07T20:45:00+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://mrelectron.github.com/blog/2011/12/07/carlin-religious-bullshit</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I found this 10 minute video by the late <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_Carlin">George Carlin</a> on <a href="http://thepiratebay.org">Pirate Bay</a>. Its funny and great viewing for the irreligious and religious alike. The video and sound are crap but the video is still viewable.</p>

<p><video width='' height='' preload='none' controls poster=''><source src='http://heterodoxic.com/video/carlin.mp4' type='video/mp4; codecs="avc1.42E01E, mp4a.40.2"'/></video></p>

<p>I don&#8217;t know what the rest of his stuff is like. For what its worth he is 2nd on this <a href="http://www.listology.com/list/comedy-central-100-greatest-standups-all-time">list</a> of the 100 greatest standup comedians.</p>

<p>After putting this up, I found 100&#8217;s of videos of Carlin on YouTube.</p>

<p>This post uses the new HTML5 video tag, which is pretty neat, so now you can put a video on your website with the same ease as you used to be able to do with an image. I think there are some issues with cross browser support - I generally use chrome (I would much rather use Firefox - but the wheels have fallen of at Mozilla and Firefox is now just a slow bloated memory and resource hog - a crying shame.) and it works well.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Octopress - Custom Domain]]></title>
    <link href="http://mrelectron.github.com/blog/2011/11/18/octopress-custom-domain/"/>
    <updated>2011-11-18T17:10:00+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://mrelectron.github.com/blog/2011/11/18/octopress-custom-domain</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This post describes the process whereby you can use your own domain name to point to your blog. Useful background information can be found <a href="http://pages.github.com/">here</a>. Look under subheadings &#8220;User &amp; Organization Pages&#8221; &amp; &#8220;Custom Domains&#8221;</p>

<p>As an example of what we are going to do, my github username is mrelectron, I have a repository accessible at the internet address http://mrelectron.github.com. But I want to access this repository using a domain name that I own called heterodoxic.com</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Assumptions</h2>

<ul>
<li>You have a working Octopress installation.</li>
<li>You own a domain name</li>
<li>You have edit / add permission for your domain name DNS records.</li>
</ul>


<h2>Step: Create CNAME file</h2>

<p>Using the editor of your choice create a file called CNAME in the source directory of your Octopress installation. On the first line put the domain name that you want to point to your Octopress installation.</p>

<p><img src="http://mrelectron.github.com/images/004.png"></p>

<h2>Step: Commit CNAME file</h2>

<p>Committing this file to the repository will signal to the github server it needs to map requests for heterodoxic.com to mrelectron.github.com</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>& git add .
</span><span class='line'>& git commit -m 'Adding CNAME file'
</span><span class='line'>& git push origin source</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<h2>Step: Modify DNS Records</h2>

<p>I cannot be specific here as DNS management user interfaces are going to vary wildly. I added a single &#8220;A&#8221; DNS record that points at 207.97.227.245 which is github.com. The @ in the image is shorthand for heterodoxic.com.</p>

<p><img src="http://mrelectron.github.com/images/005.png"></p>

<h2>Step: Fini</h2>

<p>All done, it may take some time for the change made to your DNS, to propagate around the world. If it does not work after 24 hours though, you may have a problem.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Octopress - Installation]]></title>
    <link href="http://mrelectron.github.com/blog/2011/11/18/octopress-installation/"/>
    <updated>2011-11-18T11:13:00+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://mrelectron.github.com/blog/2011/11/18/octopress-installation</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This post describes the process to install <a href="http://octopress.org">Octopress</a> on <a href="http://www.ubuntu.com/">Ubuntu Oneiric 11.10</a>. My starting point was a brand spanking new install of Oneiric on a <a href="https://www.virtualbox.org/">VirtualBox</a> virtual machine.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Assumptions</h2>

<ul>
<li>You are not logged in as root.</li>
<li>Git is installed on your computer. If not a simple sudo apt-get -y install git will suffice.</li>
<li>You have created your github account and Octopress repository, if you have not go <a href="http://heterodoxic.com/blog/2011/11/17/octopress-github/">here</a>.</li>
</ul>


<h2>Step: Get Ruby</h2>

<p>Oneiric comes with Ruby 1.8.7. Octopress depends on Ruby 1.9.2.</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>& sudo apt-get -y install ruby1.9.1-full
</span><span class='line'>& sudo update-alternatives --set ruby /usr/bin/ruby1.9.1
</span><span class='line'>& sudo env REALLY_GEM_UPDATE_SYSTEM=1 gem update --system</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<h2>Step: Test Ruby</h2>

<p>The important thing is the Ruby version is at least 1.9.2.</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>& ruby -v.
</span><span class='line'>& ruby 1.9.2p290 (2011-07-09 revision 32553) [i686-linux]
</span><span class='line'>& gem -v
</span><span class='line'>& 1.8.11</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<h2>Step: Get Octopress</h2>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>& mkdir ~/name_and_location_you_choose
</span><span class='line'>& cd ~/name_and_location_you_choose
</span><span class='line'>& git clone git://github.com/imathis/octopress.git octopress</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<h2>Step: Configure Octopress</h2>

<p>Make sure you replace uname in the read / write url below with your own github username.</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>& cd octopress
</span><span class='line'>& sudo gem install bundler
</span><span class='line'>& bundle install
</span><span class='line'>& rake install
</span><span class='line'>& rake setup_github_pages
</span><span class='line'>Enter the read/write url for your repository: git@github.com:uname/uname.github.com.git</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<h2>Step: Generate &amp; Deploy</h2>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>& rake generate
</span><span class='line'>& rake deploy</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<h2>Step: Commit Source</h2>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>& git add .
</span><span class='line'>& git commit -m 'Initial Commit'
</span><span class='line'>& git push origin source</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<h2>Step: Fini</h2>

<p>All finished, you can blog. Your blog URL is http://username.github.com.  Go <a href="http://heterodoxic.com/blog/2011/11/18/octopress-custom-domain/">here</a> if you want to map this URL to a specific domain. As a starting point for your Octopress adventure have a look around the <a href="http://octopress.org">Octopress</a> site. Go <a href="http://cheat.errtheblog.com/s/octopress">here</a> for some simple instructions on how to write your first post. Go <a href="http://octopress.org/docs/configuring/">here</a> for some simple instructions on making minor modifications to the look of your blog. Go <a href="http://cheat.errtheblog.com/s/octopress">here</a> for a tag cheatsheet.</p>

<h2>References</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://greglus.com/blog/2011/10/10/how-to-install-octopress-on-ubuntu/">Gregory A. Lussier</a></li>
<li><a href="http://blog.costan.us/2011/10/getting-mri-192-on-ubuntu-1110.html">Victor Costan</a></li>
<li><a href="http://answers.oreilly.com/topic/2845-installing-ruby-1-9-on-a-debian-or-ubuntu-system/">Adriene Lamothe</a></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Octopress - Github]]></title>
    <link href="http://mrelectron.github.com/blog/2011/11/17/octopress-github/"/>
    <updated>2011-11-17T00:27:00+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://mrelectron.github.com/blog/2011/11/17/octopress-github</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This post describes how to setup a <a href="http://github.com">github</a> account and repository that <a href="http://octopress.org">Octopress</a> will use. Github will store your data and host your blog (for free).</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Assumptions</h2>

<ul>
<li>You are using Linux</li>
<li>You do not have an existing github account.</li>
<li>After creating an Account you stay logged into github.</li>
</ul>


<h2>Step: Create Account</h2>

<p>Go <a href="https://github.com/signup/free">here</a>. The image below shows creating an account for user1999 with email youremail@gmail.com.</p>

<p><img src="http://mrelectron.github.com/images/001.png"></p>

<h2>Step: Configure Account</h2>

<p>Go <a href="http://help.github.com/linux-set-up-git/">here</a>. Follow the instructions under the 3 main subheadings.</p>

<ul>
<li>First: Download and Install Git</li>
<li>Next: Set Up SSH Keys</li>
<li>Then: Set Up Your Info</li>
</ul>


<h2>Step: Create Repository</h2>

<p>Go <a href="https://github.com/repositories/new">here</a>. The important thing you need to do here is in the <strong>project name field</strong> enter <strong>username.github.com</strong>, where username is the name you used to setup your github account. The image below shows creating a repository for user1999.</p>

<p><img src="http://mrelectron.github.com/images/002.png"></p>

<h2>Step: Fini</h2>

<p>To find how to install Octopress to use this new repository go <a href="http://heterodoxic.com/blog/2011/11/18/octopress-installation/">here</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Did Alex Die?]]></title>
    <link href="http://mrelectron.github.com/blog/2011/11/16/did-alex-die/"/>
    <updated>2011-11-16T00:27:00+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://mrelectron.github.com/blog/2011/11/16/did-alex-die</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you have not watched <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0111149">Shallow Grave</a> by the <a href="www.imdb.com/title/tt0117951/">Trainspotting</a> director <a href="http://www.imdb.com/name/nm0000965">Danny Boyle</a> then you will not care about this question, but there are 100 responses on the <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0111149/board/threads">message board</a> about Alex&#8217;s death. I have not seen that degree of interest in any film previously, so I thought I would add my opinion.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>Naturally enough I thought to add the 101st opinion to the IMDB message board but IMDB not only want you to sign up to post a message they also want to you to submit your mobile number or credit card details. Thats beyond the pale so I have to post my opinion here where noone will read it, but thats OK.</p>

<p>First of all, I never for a moment thought he was alive and did not give the issue much thought until I read some of the messages about it, so I went back and had a look at the ending. Alex is dead! Why?</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Juliet is a doctor, she would have an excellent understanding of what it would take to kill Alex</p></li>
<li><p>Alex loses a lot of blood quite quickly. The blood on the floor does belong to Alex as David has already died. Also you can see how quickly he is bleeding out because the size of the blood pool increased rapidly.</p></li>
<li><p>Assuming the police arrived early the same morning he would have been laying there bleeding for at least 3 hours, and at the rate alluded to in point 2 he would have bled out.</p></li>
<li><p>Now even if the paramedics who were standing around were going to leave the knife in and saw (as in carpenter) around the body as some people seemed to think (that is so funny!). They would be still be physically close to him, kneeling by him, keeping him warm, offering moral support and managing his shock.</p></li>
</ol>


<p>Anyway the film is great and highly recommended. Get it, and you can make up your mind if Alex died or not.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
