<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: trading | heterodoxic]]></title>
  <link href="http://mrelectron.github.com/blog/categories/trading/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mrelectron.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-05-03T01:03:42+10:00</updated>
  <id>http://mrelectron.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[MAB]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[No Secrets]]></title>
    <link href="http://mrelectron.github.com/blog/2012/05/03/no-secrets/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-03T00:03:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://mrelectron.github.com/blog/2012/05/03/no-secrets</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This post is mainly a repurposed copy of fxstreet's No Secrets ebook. which has some well known traders what the overiding principle of their success is. "No Secrets" means the secret is know the basics and apply plenty of elbow grease. There are also miscellanous trading truisms that I will add as time passes.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h1>Technical Catalysts</h1>

<h2>Sam Seiden</h2>

<p><blockquote><p>"Focus On The Lowest Trading Activity"</p></blockquote></p>

<p>When identifying where the next turn in the market will be, most traders focus on where the most trading activity took place on a chart. This is also what everyone is taught to do. I don't. I focus on the opposite, where the least amount of trades took place because this is where supply and demand is most out of balance and that's where prices turn.</p>

<h2>James Chen</h2>

<p><blockquote><p>"Knowing The Strength &amp; Weakness Single Currencies"</p></blockquote></p>

<p>Trading currencies is vastly different from trading other financial instruments. The key differentiator: currencies are traded exclusively as relative, rather than absolute, entities. Although all forex traders should be well aware of this, it warrants further emphasis that currencies are traded in pairs. What this really means is that currencies are not traded in isolation, but rather in terms of their relative values against other currencies.</p>

<p>If the dollar is weak, one should ask what exactly it is weak against. Is it weak across the board, or just against Canadian dollar, or Swiss franc, etc.? Is it strong against euro while weak against yen? When a significant bearish move occurs in EUR/GBP, was it a bearish EUR move, or a bullish GBP move, or both? These are crucial questions that all Forex traders should ask, and answer.</p>

<p>Knowing the strength/weakness statuses of SINGLE currencies, instead of just currency PAIRS, is key to understanding currency pair movements and intercurrency relationships. Pairing strongest currencies against weakest currencies is a highprobability approach. It is essential that traders knows at  all times the relative strengths and/or weaknesses of all the  single currencies that are being considered for potential trades.</p>

<h2>Adam Rosen</h2>

<p><blockquote><p>"Time Of Day : Less Is More..."</p></blockquote></p>

<p>The most significant economic data focuses around a number of basic themes including inflation, employment, growth, or lack thereof. News of this nature is typically released during the first few hours of each respective trading session. As traders react to the news, markets tend to enjoy periods of greater volatility and volume during these morning hours which are commonly known as the "active market hours".</p>

<p><blockquote><p>LON 08001000 GMT<br/>NYC 13001500 GMT<br/>TYO 24000200 GMT</p></blockquote></p>

<p>The EUR/USD (5minute) displayed with the Bollinger Bands indicator clearly shows the most significant trend began and lasted during the first 2hours of the trading day. A 'trendtrader' anticipating a breakout to the upside would have been handsomely rewarded by looking for that 'higherhigh' that did in fact occur early in the UStrading session.</p>

<h2>Cesar B. Leiceaga</h2>

<p><blockquote><p>"Trading with Pivot Points"</p></blockquote></p>

<p>I've found as a determining tool to apply in the foreign exchange markets, both daily and weekly pivot points.Some basic principals first to trading with pivots: They act as support and resistance.</p>

<p>If prices accelerate and hold above its pivot point, market participants will look to buy or turn bullish. If prices trade below a pivot point, traders will be looking to sell or short confirming the sentiment has turned bearish. Rules I apply to trade trends with pivot points</p>

<p><blockquote><p>In Uptrends: Buy dips to the pivot point and add to the position in S1 and S2. Use S3 to place a stop loss order. Use R1,R2, R3 as profit targets.</p></p><p><p>In Downtrends:Sell rallies to the pivot point and add to the position in R1 and R2. Use R3 to place a stop loss order. Use S1,S2 and S3 as profit targets.</p></p><p><p>In Ranges:Range low: Buy in S1 or S2. Stop S3 and target the daily pivot point.Range top: Sell in R1 or R2. Stop in R3 and target the daily pivot point.</p></blockquote></p>

<p>It is important to remember that these techniques applying pivot points best work in liquid pairs or majors: EUR/USD, USD/CHF, USD/JPY and GBP/USD.</p>

<h2>Ross Yamashita</h2>

<p><blockquote><p>"Scan Smarter : Not Harder"</p></blockquote></p>

<p>When studying Elliott Wave or any other wave pattern recognition theory, so many traders put too much emphasis on what the wave count is with regards to the current market.Rather than getting so caught up in where the market is in the count, I scan the markets for only 4 "high probability" patterns : Impulse, Zig Zag, Ending Diagonal and Contracting Triangles.</p>

<p>Certain aspects of these 4 high probability patterns have shown high levels of probable outcomes and they all can be fairly easy to see, even without Elliott Wave indicators or software.I trade primarily 14 currency pairs and I scan all my charts within minutes. Once I see any potential high probability patterns, I then investigate further with more analysis.</p>

<p>I'm not suggesting people should disregard all that Elliott Wave Theory has to offer : as a full understanding will help you in your trading.But ask yourself : Why am I trading?I, for one, enjoy trading and the challenges and excitement that come with it. However, the bottom line is, we're all here to make money. So, put the odds in your favor and search for the high probability patterns</p>

<h2>Valeria Bednarik</h2>

<p><blockquote><p>"Market volume with no technical indicators"</p></blockquote></p>

<p>Determining market volume could be critical when it comes to forex trading, as we understand that technical signals have higher probabilities of success when they come along with the right volume. For example, the break of the neckline of a figure, or a support or resistance level, are always considered reliable if volume is high, while pullbacks to those areas should show a lower volume, to give our signal further support.</p>

<p>However, not everyone realizes that volume indicators tend to be tricky: several of those are just providing information about the volume traded in the broker/platform that we are using to work; they can't measure the volume of the whole market. So how can we easily determine whether there is high or low volume at a certain moment?</p>

<p>The easiest way for me is mostly a visual trick: I turn to my 1 hour chart, or even 30 minutes one, when I see something that could be understood as a break or a sign. If that particular candle is at least twice as long as the average that the pair moves in that particular time frame, I understand there is high volume favoring my signal. For example, if the EUR/USD moves 25 pips per hour on average, the candle that triggers the signal should be at least of 50 pips (double the 25) or more. Easy, clean, and with no extra indicators to mess our trading strategy.</p>

<h1>Fundamental Catalysts</h1>

<h2>Aamar Hussain</h2>

<p><blockquote><p>"Adapt and Overcome"</p></blockquote></p>

<p>Always be willing and ready to adapt to the market. (a) Daily Ranges, (b) Volume and (c) Fundamentals, all provide key information and clues as to which technical analysis and trading strategies will work best in a particular environment. NO strategy or analysis method will work in all environments. If you keep a close eye on the abc and make copious notes and observations how changes in each effect market dynamics you will be able to ascertain which methods and strategies are most suited to each environment.Data and Evolution are Key.</p>

<h2>Charis Charilaou</h2>

<p><blockquote><p>"Focus on the main story... everything else is just noise"</p></blockquote></p>

<p>Markets are constantly moving and media try to publish as much information as possible in order to gain credibility and expand audiences. However, not all information is equal. You need to be able to screen out most of the news and focus on the main story. This is the only way to understand the Market and become efficient in any trading style. There is always a main story concerning a war, a political state, an economical point of view etc. This is what the market focuses on and this is what creates a trend. Everything else is just noise.</p>

<h2>John Kicklighter</h2>

<p><blockquote><p>"Know What Moves Your Trade"</p></blockquote></p>

<p>One of the most valuable lessons I have learned trading in the past few years is to first identify what fundamental driver or drivers the market deems most important for a particular currency or the market as a whole. It's easy to get caught up in reviewing all the economic indicators or headlines that cross the wires and then trying to assess what kind of impact it could have on price action. Yet, if for example yield expectations are the market's sole concern, we shouldn't waste time monitoring growth numbers and potentially confusing an otherwise straightforward forecast. Furthermore, when looking for that primary catalyst, it is important to remember that the market always boils down to the equilibrium of risk and reward in one way or another.</p>

<h2>Dirk Du Toit</h2>

<p><blockquote><p>"You need a fundamental view."</p></blockquote></p>

<p>If you use technical analysis you base your whole trading system on this principle: "The last price contains all information about price valuation".A series of such "last prices" is a pattern and a pattern is predictive of future moves.The problem very short term minded traders experience is that the Big Players as a rule ignore their "last prices". They don't even consider an intra day price as important.It is completely irrelevant to them that that price you think is a high probability indicator exists!</p>

<p>Institutions pay armies of analysts to determine what is the "content of last prices". What have been "factored in" in relation to a house "fundamental view".Institutions do technical analysis under the continuous guidance of a fundamental view.If you know what is really in the price, your technical analysis becomes really predictive because you can judgethe potential action of traders with a larger time horizon and outlook than yours.</p>

<p>Simple technical systems become effective and profitable as part of a proper fundamental view. Ignore the fundamentals at your own risk! (And please, don't confuse economic data releases with the real drivers behind currency prices.)</p>

<h1>Risk Control</h1>

<h2>Elizabeth Gregory</h2>

<p><blockquote><p>"Plan the trade, trade the plan"</p></blockquote></p>

<p>What usually hurts novice traders is poor risk management; choosing wildly optimistic profit targets in order to justify cripplingly painful stops and staying in losing trades far beyond the original plan. It's human nature to take profit on winning positions too early for fear of losing small accrued profits and to hold onto losing positions (and worse, doubling down!) in the vain hope that the market must surely reverse soon.</p>

<p>One of the best ways to enforce good discipline is to ensure that when entering any trade, there are always predetermined stop and take profit orders entered and that the amount of capital you risk is AT LEAST as much as you aim to win.The ONLY adjustments that should be made after that should be to trail the stop tighter (to minimize losses/guarantee profits) while extending the profit target.</p>

<p>Once the action starts, you can be sure the trade will succeed or fail within the reasonable riskreward criteria that was decided with a cool head. What's more, when relying on orders and not staring fixedly at every tick on open positions, trading becomes a much less stressful and emotional experience.</p>

<h2>Alberto Munoz</h2>

<p><blockquote><p>"Risk/Reward Ratio vs Investment Horizon"</p></blockquote></p>

<p>My main discovery about trading in the last months is that risk/reward ratio should be directly proportional to your investment horizon. That is, when you're trading in very short time frames, scalping for a few pips, then you're risk/reward ratio should be low, even lower than 1. The concept behind this is that it makes no sense to hold a position too much time waiting for a profit which is twice the stop loss: it won't work as the market noise will probably hit our tight stop. On the other hand, when trading on higher time frames (i.e. daily) risk/reward ratios should be high, above 2 or more, as we have time enough to reach our target.</p>

<h2>Yohay Elam</h2>

<p><blockquote><p>"Never risk more than 2% of your account at once"</p></blockquote></p>

<p>As with anything new, you're likely to make mistakes, learn from them, and then improve. Many new traders risk too much of their account, and burn it out before learning anything.Money management is the "secret" to avoiding this fate. This abstract idea can go down to the 2% rule. Making 2% an overriding priority means no stop loss movements, using lower leverage, making a bigger initial deposit, having higher spreads, or anything, else that will keep the losses limited. Some things are more comfortable to do than others, but keeping this rule will likely yield in better results for newbies in the long run : keep them away from burning their account.</p>

<h2>Ron Schelling</h2>

<p><blockquote><p>"Never use more than 2% equity risk when I place stops."</p></blockquote></p>

<p>I am in trading since 1983, a time that there was no computer or realtime data, just a phone ! Data came in by telex and I draw the charts by hand, actually the best training I ever got. Today we have almost everything for free, realtime data, online brokerage, realtime charts etc.Still most traders make no money, at least not constant. I am happy to survive it so far and maybe this comes from discipline I learned in aviation to fly aircraft using strictly checklist for each part of the flight.</p>

<p>The best trading tip I can give you and which helped me to survive > 25 years of trading is as follows: "Never use more than 2% equity risk when I place stops."For example, if I have 4 positions and all stopped out, I will lose max. 2% of clients account. So the stop level is important and so the number of contracts .If there is high volatility and a high daily range, than my number of contracts are smaller. If there is low volatility and smaller daily ranges, than my number of contracts are bigger. At any time, being stopped out in all positions, I will lose max. 2% on equity.</p>

<h1>Market Behavior &amp; Psychology</h1>

<h2>Keagan York</h2>

<p><blockquote><p>"Head not Heart!"</p></blockquote></p>

<p>It is always hard to take a loss. However, the first rule that needs to be adhered to by a novice trader is that positions can and will go against you and that stop losses are an important part of any trading strategy. I have been in the position where I have gotten emotionally attached to a position and didn't trade with my head. On occasion, things ended up working out. However, more often than not, I ended up losing more money. In these situations, not only do you lose money but you also end up missing out on better opportunities because your ability to trade is compromised by the funding the losing position. So remember think with your head, not your heart and make the tough call!</p>

<h2>Joseph Trevisani</h2>

<p><blockquote><p>"Be modest in your confidence and thankful in your profits"</p></blockquote></p>

<p>When our trades lose money, whatever our logic, we can be sure we were not alone. But we can equally be sure that we were in the minority. Had we been in the majority the market would have performed as anticipated. The market decision process is that simple. It is a matter of putting our behavior in line with the majority as often as we can. The most effective tool to achieve that is our own empirically tested market psychology. We are the market, if only we can let ourselves mimic the mind of the market and not permit individuality to rule our decisions.</p>

<h2>Shawn Powell</h2>

<p><blockquote><p>"Count to ten rule"</p></blockquote></p>

<p>If you are in that much of a hurry, you probably haven't done your analysis or you might be chasing a move. Do you know your stop and take profit levels? One quick review, count to ten and then take the trade.</p>

<h2>Dr Sivaraman</h2>

<p><blockquote><p>"Pay attention to quick, false and intentional moves"</p></blockquote></p>

<p>1.Quick moves are false moves in the market : use such moves to do counter trades once the new low or high is not breached for 30 min in a session.2. False moves may be seen before the data release and the intentional move may be seen after the data : a drop before we may initiate buy and a rise before data we can initiate sell to quickly close in or keep stop at entry in in first 30 min of entry.</p>

<h2>Derek Frey</h2>

<p><blockquote><p>"you can't predict the future..."</p></blockquote></p>

<p>The biggest thing that got me from a losing trader to a winning trader was the realization that I did not have to know the future to be successful. Many new traders think that trading is all about know what is coming next, but of course no one can really predict the future. So for me realizing that this business is all about playing the odds rather than knowing the future was the single biggest epiphany that got me over the hump. I now focus on Harmonics and the statistical edge that they provide. If you don't know what your edge is, you don't have one!</p>

<h1>Trend Following</h1>

<h2>Greg Michalowski</h2>

<p><blockquote><p>"Three's a Crowd"</p></blockquote></p>

<p>Most people know the old saying "Two's Company. Three's a Crowd". I use that easily remembered saying, to help define a nontrending forex market that is likely to transition into a trending market.I can use the Three's Company setup on a 5 minute, hourly or daily chart. The "two" in my trade are two moving averages.</p>

<p>Specifically, I use the 100 and 200 bar Simple Moving Average. The "three" in my trade is the current price. When the 100 and 200 bar MA converge with the price, it says to me it is time for the price : the third wheel in the group : to move away. Traders should simply look for a price break and go with the break. Risk is initially defined by using the 100 bar moving average. Should the price move back over the 100 bar MA look to exit the trade.The bonus is traders who recognize the setup, should also have confidence to stay with the trend.</p>

<p>The reason is if you can anticipate a trend move, focus is confidently on the trend. Also risk is defined and limited. Traders can use a cross over the 38.2% Fibonacci retracement as an exit, or simply wait for the price to cross back over the 100 bar MA. Often because the setup starts a trend, the price will reach a support level, tire and rest. This provides the trader with a number of options for a graceful exit.</p>

<h2>Mohammed Isbeer</h2>

<p><blockquote><p>"Never go against the general trend"</p></blockquote></p>

<p>Identifying the general trend whether on the short/medium/long term is the most essential, and when you figure it out, you stay with the trend. You buy on dips or sell on rallies according whether it's a down or up trend, but you never bet on a correction against the general trend.Committing to this rule will protect you from sudden and huge losses, as well as guarantees that you will be able to gain the most from a trend when the right moves happen.</p>

<h2>Kathy Lien</h2>

<p><blockquote><p>"Stick With the Trend: Tops &amp; Bottoms only evident in Hindsight"</p></blockquote></p>

<p>The trend is your friend may be one of the oldest maxims in trading but it is also one of the most important when it comes to the forex market. Trends in currencies can last for days, weeks and sometimes even months. Currencies are typically seen as little confidence indicators for a country and the outlook for a country usually gets progressively better or worse.</p>

<p>Also, due to the significant amount of participation and speculation in the forex market, when sentiment turns in one direction, it can be very strong and lead to sharp moves in currency values. As a result, I have generally found far greater success going with a trend than fading it. Tops and bottoms are only evident in hindsight and it is much better to wait for confirmation that a trend has ended than to arbitrarily pick a top or bottom.</p>

<p>The biggest fear of many traders is that they buy the top or sell the low. To avoid this, I prefer to join a trend at value. There are many ways to identify the value points through the use of my Double Bollinger Band Strategy or retrace to a Moving Average.</p>

<h2>Raghee Horner</h2>

<p><blockquote><p>"Don't Fight the Daily Market Trend"</p></blockquote></p>

<p>Over the years I have been using the daily timeframe for what I call Directional Bias. The reason for this is because I don't want to fight the larger, more dominant trend : it's like swimming upstream otherwise : much more effort it needed. The dominant trend reflects the psychology of the market.</p>

<p>Remember that all those candles or bars on your chart are simply graphing human emotions: fear, greed, confusion, anticipation.The daily chart will also assist me in determining whether my intraday set ups are trendfollowing or countertrend. If I am going to enter a market in a direction that is opposite the daily's Directional Bias I want to be sure it's on a shortterm time frame like a five, 15, or 30minute so in this was I am not dependent on longerterm countertrend movement.</p>

<p>I think many traders would benefit from starting their analysis with the daily : not necessarily to trade that time frame : but the understand the dominant psychology at work in the market.</p>

<h2>Wayne McDonnell</h2>

<p><blockquote><p>"Multiple time frames to trade forex"</p></blockquote></p>

<p>I always start my trade planning by looking at the Daily chart.On the Daily chart I look to see where price is in relation to shortterm moving averages. I like to trade in the direction of the trend. This means that I'm either trading at/near the moving averages and cautious when price is far from the moving averages due to the possibility of a mean reversion.</p>

<p>Based on this analysis, I create a bias. I'm either a bull or a bear. As a bull, I look to buy dips on the smaller time frames. As a bear, I sell rallies on the smaller time frames. Without bias, I am neutral and often don't trade at all.For example, if my daily chart bias is bearish, I look for resistance and over bought conditions on the lower time frames. If we are at a Daily R Pivot that is near a psychological round number, I see this as possible resistance.</p>

<p>I then check the 15 min stochs to see if there is any steam left in the current "up" move. If not, I'll look for moving averages crossing down, lower lows and such. The rest is trade management... and praying doesn't hurt.</p>

<h1>Miscellany</h1>

<h2>Supply &amp; Demand</h2>

<p>Thomas A. Meyers "Price movements are simply the reflection of changes in supply and demand. The technician does not care what the underlying forces of a shift in supply and demand are, rather he is interested in what occurs. If demand is greater than supply, prices will increase. On the other hand, if supply is greater than demand, prices will decline. The study of market prices is all that is necessary."</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[R Multiples]]></title>
    <link href="http://mrelectron.github.com/blog/2012/05/01/r-multiples/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-01T23:57:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://mrelectron.github.com/blog/2012/05/01/r-multiples</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This post describes R-Multiples or Risk Multiples a trading money management concept made popular by Van Tharp.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>R is simply the dollar risk per trade. It's nothing but a reward-to-risk ratio. Dr. Tharp reveals the great secret of trading: The golden rule of trading is to keep losses at a level of 1 R as often as possible and to make profits that are high-R multiples.</p>

<p>To calculate the R Multiple for a trade:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>Rmultiple = ProfitLoss / InitialRisk</p></blockquote></p>

<p>Example:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>InitialRisk: AUD175<br/>ProfitLoss: AUD350<br/>Rmultiple = 350 / 175<br/>Rmultiple = 2.00</p></blockquote></p>

<p>When I look at my results in terms of multiples of R I can easily tell how good or bad the trades were. I like to think of R-Multiples as telling you the efficiency of your system.</p>

<p>Also recording trades in terms of R-Multiples allows you to easily calculate your system's expectancy.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Expectancy]]></title>
    <link href="http://mrelectron.github.com/blog/2012/05/01/expectancy/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-01T23:56:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://mrelectron.github.com/blog/2012/05/01/expectancy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This post describes expectancy one of the most important aspects of trading.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>This article was written by <a href="http://www.tradermike.net/archives">TraderMike</a>.</p>

<p>Expectancy along with position sizing are probably the two most important factors in trading/investing success.</p>

<p>In simple terms, expectancy is the average amount you can expect to win (or lose) per dollar at risk. Here's the formula for expectancy:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>Expectancy = (ProbabilityWin * AvgWin) - (ProbabilityLoss * AvgLoss)</p></blockquote></p>

<p>As an example let's say that a trader has a system that produces winning trades 30% of the time. That trader's average winning trade nets 10% while losing trades lose 3%. So if he were trading $10,000 positions his expectancy would be:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>(0.3 * $1,000) - (0.7 * $300) = $90</p></blockquote></p>

<p>So even though that system produces losing trades 70% of the time the expectancy is still positive and thus the trader can make money over time. You can also see how you could have a system that produces winning trades the majority of the time but would have a negative expectancy if the average loss was larger than the average win:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>(0.6 * $400) - (0.4 * $650) = -$20</p></blockquote></p>

<p>In fact, you could come up with any number of scenarios that would give you a positive, or negative, expectancy. The interesting thing is that most of us would feel better with a system that produced more winning trades than losers. The vast majority of people would have a lot of trouble with the first system above because of our natural tendency to want to be right all of the time. Yet we can see just by those two examples that the percentage of winning trades is not the most important factor in building a system. As Dr. Van K. Tharp points out:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>... your trading system should have a positive expectancy and you should understand what that means. The natural bias that most people have is to go for high probability systems with high reliability.</p></p><p><p>We all are given this bias that you need to be right. We're taught at school that 94 percent or better is an A and 70 or below is failure. Nothing below 70 is acceptable. Everyone is looking for high reliability entry systems, but its expectancy that is the key.</p></p><p><p>And the real key to expectancy is how you get out of the markets not how you get in. How you take profits and how you get out of a bad position to protect your assets. The expectancy is really the amount you'll make on the average per dollar risked.</p></p><p><p>If you have a methodology that makes you 50 cents or better per dollar risked, that's superb. Most people don't. That means if you risk $1,000 that you'll make on the average $500 for every trade - that's averaging winners and losers together.</p></blockquote></p>

<p>In "Trade Your Way to Financial Freedom" Dr. Tharp defines the following four components of expectancy.</p>

<ul>
<li>Reliability, or what percentage of time you make money.</li>
<li>The relative size of your profits compared with your losses.</li>
<li>Your cost of making a trade. (commission &amp; slippage)</li>
<li>How often you get the opportunity to trade.</li>
</ul>


<p>The fourth item in that list is a very important and often overlooked aspect of trading. If you had two systems that both had the same positive expectancy, let's say $100, the system that produced more trades would make more money over time. For example, system A produces 3 trades per week while system B produces 10 trades per week. After just one week B would have made $1,000 while A would only have made $300. Gary B. Smith has discussed this before:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>I think of my equity as inventory. In that respect, my goal is to maximize not profit per dollar, but profit per dollar per day. In essence, I try to make a small percentage on my equity each day, but compound that amount as rapidly as possible.</p></blockquote></p>

<p>And in another article Gary said:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>Q: What aspect of trading took you the longest to learn?</p></p><p><p>I'd say the view that my equity is the same as a retailer's inventory. Your profit per piece doesn't matter if you never turn your inventory. And your turnover doesn't matter if you're losing money on each sale. What matters is the turnover times profit per piece.</p></p><p><p>That's the same concept I try to apply to my trading. I start with $1 and want to figure out how to quickly turn that into $10. Most people focus on buying a stock at $20 and selling it at $40, and they rarely care how long it takes them to do that.</p></p><p><p>However, if during that time I can buy 10 $20 stocks and sell them each at a 10% gain, I'm way ahead if I continue to compound my equity.</p></blockquote></p>

<p>To touch on the importance of the size of your equity and position sizing I'll use part of a snowball fight metaphor that Tharp uses in his book:</p>

<p>Imagine that you are hiding behind a large wall of snow. Someone is throwing snowballs at your wall, and your objective is to keep your wall as large as possible for maximum protection.</p>

<p>Thus, the metaphor immediately indicates that the size of the wall is a very significant variable. If the wall is too small, you couldn't avoid getting hit. But if the wall is massive, then you are probably not going to get hit. The size of your initial equity is a little like the size of the wall. In fact, you might consider your starting capital to be a wall of money that protects you. The more money you have, assuming all the other variables (the components of expectancy listed above) are the same, the more protection you will have.</p>

<p>Now imagine that the person throwing snowballs at you has two different kinds of snowballs -- white snowballs and black snowballs. White snowballs are a little like winning trades. They simply stick to the wall of snow and increase its size.</p>

<p>Imagine that black snowballs dissolve snow and make a hole in the wall equivalent to their size. You might think of black snowballs as "antisnow." Thus, if a lot of black snowballs were thrown at the wall, it would soon disappear or at least have a lot of holes in it. Black snowballs are a lot like losing trades -- they chip away at your wall of security.</p>

<p>Tharp continues walking the reader through different scenarios and possibilities. Like considering the relative sizes of the snowballs of each color. What happens to your wall after being hit by some black boulders of snow? Or considering how the rate at which snowballs are thrown affects the wall.</p>

<p>You can see how important each aspect of expectancy is as well as the huge importance of both the amount of equity (the size of your wall) and position-sizing (which will determine the size of the snowballs).</p>

<p>Expectancy, position-sizing and other aspects of money management are far more important than discovering the holy grail entry system or indicator(s).</p>

<p>Unfortunately entry techniques are where the vast majority of books and talking heads focus their attention. You could have the greatest stock picking system in the world but unless you take these money management issue into consideration you may not have any money left to trade the system.</p>

<p>Having a system that gives you a positive expectancy should be in the forefront of your mind when putting together a trading plan.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Order Types]]></title>
    <link href="http://mrelectron.github.com/blog/2012/04/29/order-types/"/>
    <updated>2012-04-29T03:57:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://mrelectron.github.com/blog/2012/04/29/order-types</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This post is about execution orders in particular about the types of orders you can make when you execute a trade.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Order Types</h2>

<p>Most brokers allow traders 2 different ways in which they can enter the market. Traders have the option to either enter the market instantly or wait for a predetermined level to be reached and then automatically enter the market. These are known as Market orders and Pending orders.</p>

<h3>Market Orders</h3>

<p>These are the most basic way of trading. A trader will decide which way they think the market is going and either buy or sell at the current price. After determining the size of their position the trader simply has to click on buy or sell and the trade is opened instantly by their broker.</p>

<h3>Pending Orders</h3>

<p>There are 3 different types of pending orders that can be placed on most brokers" platforms; stop order, limit order &amp; OCO order. Pending orders are placed a specific levels predetermined by the trader. The trader will place either a buy or sell trade and wait for the market to reach the level they are waiting for before their order goes "live".</p>

<h3>Stop Orders</h3>

<p>These types of orders can be placed when the trader wants to wait for the market to reach a certain level before entering their trade. These types of orders can be placed when the market is ranging (no clear direction) either above or below the range. The traders order is triggered when the market moves up or down to their predetermined level depending on the direction they are expecting.</p>

<h3>Buy Stop</h3>

<p>As you can see below the pending buy order is placed above the current market price. The trader expects the price to continue rising after they have been triggered into the trade.</p>

<p><img src="/images/20120429-0001.png"></p>

<h3>Sell Stop</h3>

<p>As you can see the pending order is placed below the current market price. The trade expects the market to continue falling after they have been entered into the trade</p>

<p><img src="/images/20120429-0002.png"></p>

<h3>Limit Orders</h3>

<p>These types of orders can be placed when the trade wants to wait for the market to reach a certain level before entering their trade. They are different to stop orders. As we know, when a trader places a buy/sell stop they are expecting the market to continue moving in the same direction. Limit orders however are slightly different. The trade will place a buy or sell limit at a higher or lower price than the current market price. However they will expect the market to "bounce" of their entry price and move in the opposite direction. For example a buy limit may be placed when the trader expects the market to move up before moving down therefore placing a sell limit at a higher price than the current market price hoping to enter the trade at a better price.</p>

<h3>Buy Limit</h3>

<p>As you can see the trader expects the market to slightly fall before rising. They have placed a buy limit below the current market price.</p>

<p><img src="/images/20120429-0003.png"></p>

<h2>Sell Limit</h2>

<p>As you can see below the trader expects the market to rise before falling. They have placed a sell limit order above the current market price.</p>

<p><img src="/images/20120429-0004.png"></p>

<h3>OCO Orders</h3>

<p>Many brokers allow traders the option to place OCO orders. OCO means "order cancels other". These are 2 orders placed on the same currency pair. One is a buy stop and the other is a sell stop. The trader expects the market to move either up or down and dosnt want to miss out on the move. They place a buy stop above the current market price and a sell stop below the current market price. When either the buy or sell have been triggered the other pending trade is automatically cancelled.</p>

<p><img src="/images/20120429-0005.png"></p>

<h3>GTC Orders</h3>

<p>These types of orders are an "add on" to the 3 types of orders we"ve just discussed. GTC means Good Till Cancelled. This means that the order placed by the trader will remain in the market until cancelled by them. Many brokers also allow the option to add a "valid until" part to a pending trade. This means that predetermined time can be set by the trader before the trade is closed by the broker automatically.</p>

<p><img src="/images/20120429-0006.png"></p>

<p><img src="/images/20120429-0007.png"></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Magic of Compounding]]></title>
    <link href="http://mrelectron.github.com/blog/2012/04/29/the-magic-of-compounding/"/>
    <updated>2012-04-29T02:07:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://mrelectron.github.com/blog/2012/04/29/the-magic-of-compounding</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Have you ever wondered how Warren Buffet made his millions? In this post we look at the concept of compounding. If you are at all interested in financial security for your children, you should be drumming this into your child's head as soon as they can walk.</p>

<p>It's a crime that school is the worse possible preparation for life. Having said that I did learn compounding at school, though it was in Mathematics and maybe I did not have the brains to realise its application in the real world.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><blockquote><p>Thank you to Richard Stoyeck for this article. Richard's background includes being a limited partner at Bear Stearns, Senior VP at Lehman Brothers, Kuhn Loeb, Arthur Andersen, and KPMG. Educated at Pace University, NYU, and Harvard.</p></blockquote></p>

<p>Some of you know about this, some of you don't. Either way I'm going to give you the basics of compounding, plus a couple of new slants on the concept. I suggest you read The Magic of Compounding not just once, but several times. If you have children, print this write-up and give it to them to read. If they master this concept they will become rich.</p>

<h2>The Basics</h2>

<p>Compounding describes how numbers, or money, can grow. Numbers can grow in an arithmetic progression, for example 2,4,6,8,10,12 or 3,6,9,12,15,18, where one unit is added on at each step in the progression and that action provides the growth, or, numbers can grow exponentially, 2,4,8,16,32,64. In an exponential progression the increase comes by doubling the number at each step in the progression. See the difference? This is compounding.</p>

<p>Now the really amazing part, the magic, comes when you see how fast compounding will make money grow. And guess what! That's right, I've got a little game to play with you, a little story to tell, that will illustrate this principle. This puzzle is as old as J.P. Morgan's moustache comb, so if you've already been schooled in compounding you've heard it before. But didn't I tell you to read this section several times? OK, then, solve the puzzle with us once more while I tell it for the first time to the children for whom "The Magic of Compounding" has just been printed out.</p>

<h2>The Puzzle</h2>

<p>I'm a wealthy and generous man, and I want to hire you to work for me for one month. Since I'm also flexible, I give you a choice: you can choose to be payed the entire month's salary up front on the first day of your employment, or, I will pay you 1 cent the first day and I'll double your pay every day for the rest of the month, but you won't get the money until the last day of the month. So on the first day you'll work 8 whole hours and you'll have 1cent coming to you. But on the second day you'll earn 2cents. Hold on, it gets better, the 3rd day with me you'll have earned 4 cents, the day after that 8 cents and so on. Saturdays and Sundays are included just to give you a chance. Oh, by the way, if you take your pay all at once on the first day I'll give you a million bucks ($1,000,000.00) cash. Seems like an easy choice, doesn't it?</p>

<p>Well, you decide for yourself . Now let's look at how much the individual who picked the penney-a-day plan are going to have at month's end. Remember, on the one hand $1,000,000.00. On the other hand::</p>

<p><div class='bogus-wrapper'><notextile><figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>&lt;/p>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;pre>&lt;code>Day Amount
</span><span class='line'>01  0.01
</span><span class='line'>02  0.02
</span><span class='line'>03  0.04
</span><span class='line'>04  0.08
</span><span class='line'>05  0.16
</span><span class='line'>06  0.32
</span><span class='line'>07  0.64
</span><span class='line'>08  1.28
</span><span class='line'>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;p></span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure></notextile></div></p>

<p>Hey folks, it's day eight, you're up to $1.28 and you only have a month. Maybe you are better off taking the one shot deal, the million dollars. Let's see what happens::</p>

<p><div class='bogus-wrapper'><notextile><figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
<span class='line-number'>15</span>
<span class='line-number'>16</span>
<span class='line-number'>17</span>
<span class='line-number'>18</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>&lt;/p>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;pre>&lt;code>Day Amount
</span><span class='line'>09  2.56
</span><span class='line'>10  5.12
</span><span class='line'>11  10.24
</span><span class='line'>12  20.48
</span><span class='line'>13  40.96
</span><span class='line'>14  81.82
</span><span class='line'>15  163.84
</span><span class='line'>16  327.68
</span><span class='line'>17  655.36
</span><span class='line'>18  1310.72
</span><span class='line'>19  2621.44
</span><span class='line'>20  5242.88
</span><span class='line'>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;p></span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure></notextile></div></p>

<p>By the way, did any of you ask me what month of the year we're in? Is it February with 28 days, or leap year with 29 days, or September with 30 days, or December with 31 days? You should realize that it's going to make a difference. Do you want the million dollars? Ask your kids again which they would choose? Let's continue::</p>

<p><div class='bogus-wrapper'><notextile><figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
<span class='line-number'>15</span>
<span class='line-number'>16</span>
<span class='line-number'>17</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>&lt;/p>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;pre>&lt;code>Day Amount
</span><span class='line'>21  10,485.76
</span><span class='line'>22  20,971.52
</span><span class='line'>23  41,943.04
</span><span class='line'>24  83,886.08
</span><span class='line'>25  167,772.16
</span><span class='line'>26  335,544.32
</span><span class='line'>27  671,772.16
</span><span class='line'>28  1,342,177.28
</span><span class='line'>29  2,684,354.56
</span><span class='line'>30  5,368,709.12
</span><span class='line'>31  10,737,418.24
</span><span class='line'>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;p></span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure></notextile></div></p>

<p>If you work for me in September with 30 days you make over $5,000,000. In December it's over $10,000,000! I have never met the child who didn't leap at the $1,000,000 on day one. This is because human brains think arithmetically, not exponentially. You might say that we are hardwired to think in this linear way, that the software in our brains compels us to think about progressions as being simple arithmetic ones. Luckily though, how we think about things, our prejudices, our attitudes, and our mindsets, can all be changed and worked with. We can update the software! We can consciously change the way we think about numbers, money and investing by absorbing new information, namely, that when you make your money compound you can get rich sooner rather than later.</p>

<p>Teach your children to live a balanced life, and also help them master this concept and you will have very happy and very rich children. In stocks make money at the bottom by buying depressed securities that are going to come right back, making you a fortune as they rocket off the bottom. In the future make money with the Warren Buffet concept, or classical Graham and Dodd analysis.</p>

<h2>The New Slant</h2>

<p>Really understanding compounding will make all the difference in investing. I believe that Warren Buffett, the world's greatest investor, is hardwired to think geometrically. He is rich beyond dreams because he totally gets the magic of compounding, and he executes on the concept. I am going to get these numbers wrong because I'm doing them from memory but it doesn't matter. You'll get the concept. Buffett started a partnership way back when. He had a number of limited partners invest with him, and he took 20% of the gains. In the late 1960s he terminated the partnership with his famous letter,</p>

<p><blockquote><p>"When you no longer understand the way the game is played, it's time to leave the game."</p></blockquote></p>

<p>I'm paraphrasing, even though it's in quotes. Buffet took about $100 million out of that first partnership for himself, so he was working with $100 million, keep that in mind. In 1974 when the bear market bottomed, it might have been early 1975, he started another rise...he took over Berkshire Hathaway. Buffet, since the 1970's, has been getting a compounded (remember that means exponential) growth rate of about 22 to 24%.</p>

<p>This is where I introduce you to the cousin of the Magic of Compounding, which is called the Rule of 72. With the Rule of 72 you can calculate how long it will take you to double your money at any given rate of return. OK? Let's take an example. If you're earning 12% on your money and you want to know how long it will take to double it (we're compounding, remember?) divide 72 by 12, and your answer is 6. It will take 6 years to double your money. Let's do another one. If you're getting 6% on your money, divide 72 by 6 and you'll see that it will take 12 years to double. If you're getting 9%, it's 72 divided by 9, or 8 years to double up.</p>

<p>As for Warren Buffett, he's getting 22% on his money. This means you divide 72 by 22 and gee, in only 3.27 years, or every 3 years and 4 months, he doubles his money. Since he's been at it about 35 years with that $100 million he had to play with, he's doubled his original $100 million almost nine times. You get that by taking 35 years and dividing by a double every 3 years and 4 months. It equals 10.70, or let's go with nine doubles to adjust for a rate of compounding that is varying. The key point is he's not making 9 times his money with the $100 million, that would be an arithmetic progression that would give him $900 million. He's making nine doubles, a geometric or compounded progression. Let's see how that works::</p>

<p><div class='bogus-wrapper'><notextile><figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
<span class='line-number'>15</span>
<span class='line-number'>16</span>
<span class='line-number'>17</span>
<span class='line-number'>18</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>&lt;/p>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;pre>&lt;code>Starting Amount : 100,000,000
</span><span class='line'>Time Periods    : Nine 3 Year, 4 month periods
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>Per TimeTaken   CompoundedGain
</span><span class='line'>01  03Y4M       00,200,000,000
</span><span class='line'>02  06Y8M       00,400,000,000
</span><span class='line'>03  10Y0M       00,800,000,000
</span><span class='line'>04  13Y4M       01,600,000,000
</span><span class='line'>05  16Y8M       03,200,000,000
</span><span class='line'>06  20Y0M       06,400,000,000
</span><span class='line'>07  23Y4M       12,800,000,000
</span><span class='line'>08  26Y8M       25,600,000,000
</span><span class='line'>09  30Y0M       51,200,000,000
</span><span class='line'>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;p></span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure></notextile></div></p>

<p>I believe Buffet is worth about $47 billion. It doesn't matter, he is somewhere in his ninth double. This is the magic of compounding! Also, he never sells. This means his money is doubling every three years and four months with no tax consequences. He gets taxed only when he sells. Under normal conditions, the money compounds until he dies, then it's taxed at a capital gains rate in the far distant future. In Buffett's case, he's giving most of his wealth to the Gates' foundation to benefit society.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
